Good evening. Good evening everyone. I'm
now calling to order this meeting of of
Lancaster City Council for August 26,
2025. A few reminders at the top of the
meeting this evening. This meeting and
its participants are being recorded.
Please take a moment uh to silence your
phones and devices if you haven't done
so already. Uh during this meeting uh we
will have opportunities for public
comment. The first general public
comment uh period is for residents that
have registered in advance to speak
about items that are not on the agenda.
Residents uh may also comment on
individual items on our legislative
agenda, which is item nine on the agenda
tonight. Finally, a second public
comment period will be at the end of the
agenda for any other speakers wishing to
address council.
All speakers will be reminded to please
begin with their name and their block of
residents for our meeting record um and
address their comments toward council.
Please be advised that public comment is
not a question and answer period. All
comments are limited to three minutes
per speaker. And to keep time, I will be
using this light here. It will turn
green when the speaker begins. It will
flash yellow when there is one minute
remaining and flash red when three
minutes has been exhausted. Uh if a
speaker continues after three minutes,
they will be asked to end their
comments. I appreciate everyone's
cooperation uh in keeping equal time and
maintaining order. Speakers addressing
city council, members of the public, and
members of council are expected to
conduct themselves in an orderly manner
and remain respectful of others. And now
for all those who are willing and able,
please rise for the pledge of
allegiance.
Mr. Harris, would you please call the
role of members?
>> Yes, Madam President. Mr. Royo
>> here.
>> I'm sorry, Mr. Med.
>> Mr. Police here.
>> Miss Greg. Miss Diaz
>> here.
>> Mr. Hirs
>> President B
>> here. Councilors Amed and Craig are
excused this evening.
>> We will move then to the approval of our
minutes from the August 12th, 2025
regular meeting of council.
>> Motion to approve.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second.
Councilors, any comments on our meeting
minutes?
>> Hearing none. Mr. Harris.
>> Mr. Royal.
>> I. Mr. Cle I
>> Mr. D
>> I
>> Mr. Hersh
>> and President B
>> I
>> councilors before we continue on with
our agenda I would like to ask your
consent to move the report of the
president of council to this point in
the meeting. Are there any objections
from councel?
Thank you so much for that. Um I I asked
to do this because I do have an item
under that uh part of the agenda that
I'd like to speak to this evening. Uh so
the first uh first part of the report is
a motion. I would like to make a motion
that council direct the solicitor and
the planning bureau to draft a zoning
ordinance amendment in accordance with
applicable law to legislatively address
the land use of data centers to protect
the impacts on the community for
presentation at the October committee
meeting. Further, council requests that
the city planning commission review the
proposed legislation and make
recommendations to council regarding the
same.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second. Members
of council, um I'm presenting this
motion this evening so we can begin the
process of updates to our zoning
ordinance to address the land use for
data centers and and in fact introduce a
separate use. Um, as part of this
process leading up to this, um, leading
up to council considering this
ordinance, a hearing will be held as,
uh, as with all zoning ordinance
amendments, um, to solicit input and
concerns from the public. That hearing
will be held in accordance with the
requirements of the municipalities
planning code, which will also include
review of the proposed ordinance by the
Lancaster County Planning Commission as
required.
Are there any additional comments on the
motion? Council
President,
>> Councelor Royo,
>> I just wanted to thank you for making
this motion. I think as many folks are
probably here tonight for um I think
it's probably long overdue that we start
considering um our zoning and what does
it mean and how does it reflect the
community that we want to build here.
So, uh I'm looking forward to hearing
the recommendations from the planning
commission.
>> Thank you. Further comments from
council,
>> if I may. President Council Diaz,
>> will there be opportunity for the
members of the community to speak
against or for um anything that they
feel that is not in co basically
possibly not in the way they wish to
have this um proposal plan be done for
the IIA data center? Yes, councelor
Diaz, the process of uh this will be an
ordinance that we will um move to uh we
will discuss. So it will be presented at
a committee meeting uh in October as
mentioned in the motion. It will be
presented for a first reading in front
of council and then a second reading
which will also include a public hearing
which is required. Um the planning
commission will uh review the
legislation. So they will also discuss
it at their public meeting. So there
will be um several at least four if not
additional uh public uh input um places
where there could be input from the
public on any proposed ordinance that
comes out of uh this action.
>> Would there be anyone um from the core I
think it's called core war um data
company that's going to be available to
speak or answer any questions to the
public? I'm not necessarily sure about
that because that's going to depend on
the processes, the process that will be
used to make these recommendations and
draft the ordinance. I want to stress
that um it is not uh specifically about
this project. It's about all projects
including theirs. Um so we do want to
address issues about the environmental
impacts and impacts of the community. Uh
but it is also about any future use. So,
it's not exclusive uh but certainly does
include uh their project.
>> Thank you. That's all I have.
>> Thank you. Um and counselors, I would
also just note that I thank you for your
patience uh in getting to this moment.
Um there is uh al always legal
considerations and and things that need
to be uh put in place. And so I'm glad
we've arrived at this moment where we
can take this action. Further comments
from council on the motion?
comments from the public on the motion.
>> Good evening. You want to just come on
up to that mic and you may need to turn
it on if you're as you're the first
speaker.
>> Hello.
>> Good evening.
>> Yes. Uh I'm Frank Archolio from Old
Trinity Place. Um, I
I have heard that any ordinance or
amendment to the zoning code that would
be introduced or requested by council,
go to the planning commission and then
be a draft of a suggested ordinance come
out of that and then obviously be
presented to council for adoption. that
that is the process.
But I've also been told that that
ordinance would not apply to the
existing two proposed data centers
because they have already received
approval letters from the city of
Lancaster.
And if that is the case, it gives me the
feeling that you are willing, we are are
willing to close the barn door long
after the horses have escaped and that
is not okay with the public. I hope that
I am mistaken and I know this is not a
question and answer period and nobody is
required to address that concern but
it's very different as to whether we're
going to go through this process for
those two centers or let me put it this
way go through a zoning process based on
the new zoning amendments that would
presum presumably be uh approved by the
council versus not being able to do
that. And and that I think is really
what we have been we the public have
been after all along to not do it in
secret and and and with no public
comment at all. to put the whole thing
through the proper process that any
special use or use not provided for
would be entitled to. So, thank you.
>> Thank you for your comments.
[Applause]
>> I do appreciate your question and your
concern. And what I can answer uh in for
this evening for the the um general
public to know um is that we would make
the zoning amendment fully enforceable
to the extent that it would be allowed
to be. I don't know the specifics and
and but that's what I can say. Um I will
also say there was something you said at
the end um that I wanted to address and
now I can't recall what it was. It's
it's completely left my mind. I
apologize for that. But I do want to say
that it will be fully enforceable. Um,
and the intention, um, the intention,
that's what it was. The intention is
that it would become, or my hope is that
it would become a conditional use that
would require, um, approvals and, um,
special exceptions that would require
public input. So, thank you. Any
additional comments from the public on
the motion?
Good evening.
>> Good evening. Uh Dan Wagel, uh Clarin
and Drive. I'm usually a speak with
notes type, so um please bear with me.
But um first I want to thank the council
for um bringing this up. As you said, I
think better late than never. Um I'm
very pleased um with what you just said
about it being enforceable for the
current projects. Um obviously we have
been extremely concerned as I know I
believe you have all been as well. So,
um, I really look forward to working
with you all in this process. Um, I urge
you all to approve the motion
unanimously tonight. Um, and we're ready
to get to work. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Any additional comments on the motion
from the public
>> hearing? None. Mr. Harris.
>> Mr. Royal.
>> I.
>> Mr. Cle.
>> Miss Diaz.
>> I.
>> Mr. H
>> I President Baker
>> I thank you councilors um I have a
second part of my report of the
president of council so I will continue
as that's what we're addressing it's
tangential um I have asked the mayor uh
continue to continue to update me on
efforts by the data center developer
Carissa Technology Parks to address air
quality and noise concerns. So um she
could not be here this evening but the
mayor has provided me with the following
updates. So, first and foremostly, an
independent evaluation of the noise
study that was completed by Carissa um
is uh is moving forward. The city has
identified um a second consultant for
consideration and interview and that
that will take place within the next uh
two weeks. So, we're making sure very
carefully that the um the firm that is
hired to do that review uh is well
verssed in specifically noise concerns
for data centers. So, we want to make
sure that their review is accurate. Uh
second, an interview with an
environmental consulting firm will take
place this week. Their work is going to
help us understand how the DP will
regulate air emissions and the nature of
the permit that was requested by this
developer because this is under their
perview. Um the city does not issue
those types of permits. We don't have
the technical expertise. So we are going
to uh uh uh get someone who does have
that expertise to review it. Um it's
also going to review how the permit is
monitored, enforced, and granted. Um, in
addition, the administration has
determined that Carissa will not be
using a cooling system that relies on
huge volumes of water. Carissa has
expressed willingness just this week to
codify this in a legally binding
community benefits agreement. So, to put
their money where their mouth is. Um,
additional information from PPL um has
been given uh regarding impacts to the
power grid, electricity rates, power
reliability, and that has been updated
on the frequently asked questions page
on the city website. Um, that's city of
lancasterpa.govdata
center uh data hyphen center. Please
note that the city does not have any
purview over the regulation of
electricity rates as much as I wish we
could, their grid, etc. Uh so we're
relying on the information provided by
PPL for this matter uh for the council
uh and the public's awareness. Um also
just to note on this topic that late
last week uh Mr. Franker Kolio has filed
an appeal to the zoning hearing board
and that appeal has been scheduled for
September the 22nd. So again that's to
the zoning hearing board. Uh counselors
that concludes my uh report of council.
Thank you for allowing me to uh move
that forward in the agenda tonight.
Next on our agenda is proclamations,
honors, awards, and resolutions of
recognition. Uh confirming, Mr. Harris,
we have none of those this evening.
>> That's correct, Madam President.
>> Thank you so much. We now move then to
our first public comment period. It's
reserved for residents who have
contacted the city clerk before
tonight's meeting uh to request the
opportunity to address council. Uh Mr.
Harris is going to be putting on the
screen the list of those residents that
contacted us ahead of time in the order
in which they were received so you'll
know when you we're coming up in the
meeting. Again, please uh address your
comments toward council. Comments are
limited to three minutes per speaker and
please begin with your name and block of
residence. Mr. Harris, uh our first
speaker, please.
>> Our first speaker is Irene Grievous.
>> Thank you.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. Um, my name is Irene
Grievous and I'm on the 400 block of uh,
West End Avenue.
Uh, I am here today to raise an issue
that has gone unresolved for four years.
This prolonged and unexplained
condemnation of my property located on
901 Matter Street. This has placed a
tremendous um amount of burden on me
personally and um needlessly removed a
home from an already strained housing uh
supply. Last month, I approached
councilwoman Faith Craig before city
council meeting to ask for her support
in introducing a petition for resolution
regarding this matter. Conveniently,
she's not here. Um,
she responded by asking me uh to email
her a draft of the petition, which I did
in good faith, promptly and
respectfully. Despite multiple
follow-ups and email and messages, I
have received no response.
This silence especially troubling
because councilwoman Craig has
personally visited my home in 2022.
She knows the conditions firsthand and
understands why no action has uh not
been possible
on on me and uh this ongoing
condemnation. I reached out not just for
help but because I believed this was a
share concern and a resolvable and a
solvable issue. At this time, I can't
help but notice the spread and ease or
the speed and ease in which permits for
AI data centers have been approved by
the city easily, often with little
resistance or delay. Yet, every one of
my 11 uh separate permit applications to
resolve this matter and move forward
with the property has been denied. This
is happening during an ongoing housing
crisis where the need for affordable
livable housing is more urgent than
ever. My property, which has been
rehabilitated and restored as a home,
has effectively been taken off the
market, but not for safety reasons, but
through prolonged inaction and
bureaucratic uh resistance. We cannot
keep saying we care about affordable
housing while actively preventing it
from becoming reality. I am asking
council and specifically Councilwoman
Craig to respond to act and to help
break this de deadlock so the property
can serve its purpose providing a home
to the community that's so desperately
needed.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker.
>> Next speaker is uh Mary Jones.
>> Mary Jones.
>> I'll call the names at the end just in
case they come in late. Our next
speaker,
>> next is Murder Neas.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. Um my name is Martin and
I'm here today to council regarding the
uh treasury offices misapply payments
for trash and water accounts. I own
several properties in the city and been
fighting with the treasury office since
2023 for payments that I have made on
time have been misapplied
um have been sent to collections and um
at the present moment uh going through
it again after just going through it in
April. Um, so, um, at this point I've
been told that, um, the penalty
assessment cannot be overwritten by the
new system. And by the way, the payments
that just were, uh, sent on July 25th
were through the new system and they
were a so. So, I believe that the issues
are human error. I don't know. I come
from a finance background, accounting
background and I believe that this is
not system related. I think the errors
are human related and I would like to
know if the council and I can work
together on a solution.
>> Thank you. I did have some additional
information on your request that I'd
like to share with you via email. Uh the
email that you use to request to make
comment. Would that be okay?
>> Yes.
>> We don't have to discuss it publicly,
but I can send you what I know have
found. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Harris. Our next speaker,
>> next speaker is Emma Burgess.
>> Hi, don't laugh at me. I brought props.
>> Evening.
>> Uh, Emma Burgess, 600 block of Mine
Street. Um, so before I start, um, I
would like to make it clear, council,
that I know you don't regulate electric
utilities. U, my three minutes today
only serve to highlight the impacts of
building this data center, um, and to
further reinforce the urgency of our
demands. If I could just really quick to
the people in the room, I would like you
to remember that if you have concerns
about electricity issues, the
Pennsylvania Utility Commission is the
governing governing body that you should
be speaking to. Um, and they also hold
bi-weekly hearings in Harrisburg, which
I would strongly encourage you to
attend. Back to council. Um, I've got
three things I'd like to address today.
First, let's talk about the increased
costs to residents that a data center
would bring. Um, for scale, the sum of
Lancaster County activity has a load of
about 700 megawws on average, which
implies a peak load of about a thousand
megawws.
Um, anyways, uh, this data center would
have a continuous load of 100 and then
300 megawatts, which would mean
increasing the load by 10 to 30%. This
is huge. Um, so increasing the demand
for power means we have to upgrade
electrical infrastructure to support it.
Um, Carissa, the developer, has said
they're upgrading the necessary
infrastructure. That's great. Um, next
we'd have to maintain the significantly
larger grid. The money for that comes
from the delivery portion of your
electrical bill. Um, last month that
portion for me uh was about 40% as shown
there. Um, here's the catch though.
Industrial customers pay significantly
less than residential customers. I know
that the FK ruling to 2023 governs a
formula. Um it's, you know,
intentionally ambiguous. Um
industrial customers pay about 44% as
much as residential customers. This
means that the increased cost for grid
maintenance will be dis
disproportionately passed on to
residents. You can all expect your bill
to go up. Um second, let's talk about
power quality. I know this isn't
something most people think or even know
about, but your power's quality ma
matters. AC power is a sine wave. Um,
when it looks good, it looks like this.
When it looks bad, it looks like this.
Um, it's due to something called
harmonics. Um, last year, Bloomberg
published a report using thousands of
sensors measuring power quality across
the nation. They compiled a list of the
homes that suffered the worst power
degradation and said that more than half
of the track households showing the
worst distortions of power quality were
located within 20 miles of significant
data center activity. This kind of
distorted power leads to damage to home
appliances in the long run. It's not
something you see immediately, but it's
something that adds up as well as
increased risks of things like
electrical fires. Um, finally, a shoot,
it's it's orange. I'd want to address
the challenge that's brought up brought
on by having a sole consumer represent
so much of the grid. Data centers are
optimized and engineered for the
protection of computers, which means
that at the smallest risk of a problem,
they switch switch to local backup
generators. That means that in an
instant, something that's like 300
megawatts would uh and hold for my
beautiful animation go offline. uh which
would decrease the uh load in this grid
from something like 1,200 megawatts to
900 because data because power grids
have to be super balanced. That's a big
problem all at once. Um which can cause
you know
cascading outages across a grid. Um I
know that engineers work really hard to
balance this but that is a problem that
needs to be addressed. Thank you very
much.
>> I hope this is helpful. I didn't cite
any sources. They're here if you want
them.
>> Thank you.
Mr. Harris, our next speaker, please.
>> Our next speaker is Tobin Burgess.
>> Okay. Thank you very much. Our next
speaker, Mr. Harris.
>> Uh Sarah Ederosa.
>> Good evening.
>> Hi.
My name is Sarah Ederosa. I'm from the
400th block of West Frederick. I'm
probably going to end up yielding most
of my time because you guys address a
lot of our concerns. So, I'll just boil
it down to three things. Number one, I
want to express appreciation for some of
the things you announced tonight.
Specifically, codifying that there won't
be water cooling uh for this facility.
Thank you for announcing that. That's
really incredible. Um and also for the
work you're doing on zoning. We want to
express that the work you do does matter
to us and we're not just here to express
when we're upset about things. Um a few
other things though. Number two, I am
still concerned about enforcability of
I'm not an expert in local governance in
these things, but it is my understanding
that a zoning ordinance would not be
enforceable, and I would love to hear
more about why that is your position.
Um, number three, the main issue that uh
the council doesn't have any ability to
really mitigate is the energy issue that
Emma just lent her incredible expertise
and design skills to. Um, and we're
still really concerned about that and we
totally understand that council does not
have a a lot that they can offer to this
fight. But what we would really love is
your support in bringing the fight to
the bodies that can. I mean, most of us
here have full-time jobs and families.
Like, we're doing this in our free time.
And so, we would really love the support
of our elected officials as we're
bringing it to the state, as we're
bringing it to regulatory bodies like
the PUC because, again, we're doing this
in our free time. So we would love to
see instead of just maybe we can't do
anything about that support and
collaboration on taking it to the body
bodies that can. So uh that's all I have
to say. I'll yield the rest of my time.
Thank you for the announcements you made
earlier.
>> Thank you very much
Sarah. I appreciate your your comments
and I would absolutely love to go to a
PUC hearing because that is where I'm
mostly concerned and where I feel most
powerless. Um, I'll also remind the
public that council is part-time and we
all have full-time jobs, too.
That's okay. I I hear your comments, so
thank you. Uh, Mr. Harris, our next
speaker,
>> our next speaker is Revy.
>> Evening,
>> Robbie. Good evening.
>> My name is Ravia Huja. I live on the 200
block of West Walnut. Um, like many
people here, I'm obviously very affected
by and concerned about the development
of the data center. I want to echo
Sarah's appreciations and something some
things that Dan said as well about some
of the things announced tonight. I think
the noise level study is really
important and welcome. Um, the codif of
the water cooling also very important.
Um, we appreciate the opportunity for
public comment. It's also something that
is critically important to be an ongoing
process. And so I just want to strongly
urge that mayor Sarra and zoning
commissioner Thrash are in attendance at
the um at the transparency hearing
October 1st. We'd love to know the full
details about all the decisions that
were made for the zoning. Um so we'd
really appreciate that. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Harris. Our next speaker
>> next speaker is Kim Keller.
>> Is Kim Keller here?
We'll go back and recall those names at
the end. Our next speaker, Mr. Harris.
>> Next is Dan Wigel.
>> Thank you. Our next speaker, Mr. Harris.
>> Next is Michelle Sales.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. Uh, can you hear me, Ari?
>> Y.
>> Uh, hi all. I'm Michelle Sales. live in
lit. Um I want to add to the
conversation on AI data centers. I know
a lot has already been said about the
environmental and financial costs which
are huge on their own. I want to draw
some attention also to what these data
centers can be empowering uh with
potential costs to our collective civil
liberties, privacy and security. So we
should all know that this data center
infrastructure is going to directly
support a lot of major tech companies
like Meta, Palunteer, Amazon. I want to
focus my comments right now on Palunteer
uh because at the same time that our
federal government is starving people of
needed funding for essential programs,
it has found plenty of money to prop up
the private sector with these massive
government contracts. Um so when we say
that AI is the future, we need to be
really clear about what the technology
is uh and what it we're going to be
using these data centers for. So
Palanteer has been the recipient of
billions in federal contracts. They have
a new 10y year 10 billion dollar
contract with the army. They're
collaborating with Doge. There's a $30
million partnership with ICE, uh, which
is already targeting folks in our
community. Uh, and I'm going to share
some sections of an open letter that was
published in May from Palunteer former
staffers and whistleblowers calling out
the company for colluding with the
authoritarian consolidation that is
underway. And they say, "Palanteer
Technologies platform grants immense
power to its users, helping control the
data, decisions, and outcomes that
determine the future of governments,
businesses, and institutions, and by
extension, all of us. Early Palanteer
staff understood the ethical weight of
building these technologies. A code of
conduct was crafted to uphold democracy,
preserve the spirit of free scientific
inquiry, and ensure responsible AI
development. Guardrails were set to
prevent discrimination, disinformation,
and abuses of power. And these
principles have now been violated and
are rapidly being dismantled at
Palanteer Tech and across Silicon
Valley. Palanteer's leadership has
abandoned its founding ideals. Public
statements have grown hostile to DEI.
Executives now employ inflammatory
language, sometimes threatening critics
with violence. Meanwhile, our democracy
faces escalating threats. Biometrics
data collection on immigrant children.
Journalists targeted science programs
defunded key US allies like Ukraine
sidelined. Trump's administration has
sought to greatly expand executive
powers while alluding to monarchy. Big
tech, including Palanteer, is
increasingly complicit, normalizing
authoritarianism under the guise of a
revolution led by oligarchs, and we must
resist this trend. And they go on, "We
no longer believe Palanteer's executives
are upholding our core values by
supporting the administration, Doge, and
dangerous expansions of executive power.
They've abandoned their responsibility
and are in violation of our code of
conduct." Um, so thank you for the
developments tonight to keep in mind uh
that we can revisit these uh the zoning
process moving forward. And I think as
we all work to shape this process uh and
how these projects shape up, we need to
be careful to not assume that all AI
development is beneficial and that we
should have a say in building a future
that we can all benefit from.
>> Thank you,
[Applause]
>> Mr. Harris. Our next speaker, please. Uh
>> next speaker is Britney Sour.
Britney, Harrisburg Pike. Um, so I'm
just here tonight as a concerned
business owner who would be directly um
impacted by one of the data centers. I
co-own a hair salon on Harrisburg Pike
directly across from one of the proposed
data centers. And it's something that,
you know, we've been very concerned
about. You know, is our
I'm glad we heard tonight about the
water that they're not going to be using
water. You know, because a lot of the
research we did, we saw, you know, it
can cause water issues. We need water to
run our business. Um, so yeah, I'm just
here to express my concern as a small
business owner of what the impacts are
going to be to my business.
>> Thank you.
>> Our next speaker, Mr. Harris.
>> Next speaker is Joela Lord.
It's Joel Lord here.
I'll recall the names at the end. Our
next speaker, Mr. Harris,
>> David Miller Glick.
>> See, David, I thought
>> Good evening.
>> Yeah, feel free to move that.
>> Apologies if this doesn't come across as
very polished. I'm uh changing some of
my comment on the fly here. Um based on
what was said earlier, um I feel a
mixture of emotion tonight. I was
angered by the lack of transparency
around the AI data center, but on the
other hand, I'm heartened to see that
council is considering uh looking at the
zoning. And I want to echo
some comments said before that I would
love to see continuing collaboration
with city council going forward. Um I'm
also concerned about the potential
energy usage and about um bills going up
but also from an environmental
perspective um the amount of energy that
uses and the cost in the environment
that it would co create to generate that
energy.
Um, I also want to close by saying that
I quite frankly do not want any new AI
centers, data centers built
anywhere near the city of Lancaster. Um,
I work in the tech industry and in my
opinion and experience, generative AI is
a scam which offers few benefits if any
to regular people like me.
But at the very least, if this center or
both centers are to be built, um I would
love to collaborate with city cl Council
going forward so that we can come to to
a good solution together. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Our next speaker, Mr. Harris.
>> Next is uh Frank Arolio.
>> Frankolio uh uh Old Trinity Place. I had
come with props tonight to uh put a
little levity to the situation. I want
to show you two different balls. One's a
football. I think we can agree on that.
The other is a baseball. They're both
balls, but they're have very different
usages and they're in very, very
different sports and they're thrown and
caught in very, very different ways. I
feel the same thing is true about data
centers versus warehouses.
And so, so how could that possibly be
done? If this is a data center, this is
a warehouse. They are not the same thing
and should never ever have been called
the same thing. As I've said before, I
appreciate your efforts and your your
action tonight to request new zoning
ordinances to deal with the data
centers. Um, my concern is whether it
really is retroactively applicable to
building permits that have already been
issued under the guise that these two
things were the same, which they're
clearly not. Um, so I guess I need to
await further um further clarification.
I know that's not, you know, your job. I
know you say you intend to to apply it
to the maximum uh effectiveness that is
legally possible and I understand that
and I just hope that that effectiveness
is substantial and not based on the
confusion that intentional or otherwise
that these are the same things. Thank
you very much.
>> Thank you.
Our
[Applause]
next speaker, Mr. Harris.
>> Next speaker is Jontel Tolen.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening. Uh Jontel Tolen, first and
only block of uh Wise Aav. Uh
I had some I changed up what I had said
a little bit because of uh the things
that you had spoke about earlier. So
thank you um for addressing the need for
dialogue and starting the meeting that
way. Uh our communities are thriving,
diverse and deeply community and deeply
invested in this issue. Uh the
perspective shared in the last meeting
added critical context that can't be
ignored. We have an opportunity to set
an example for other cities by standing
up to big tech and prioritizing our
environment, health, and future. That
starts with transparency and real
accountability. Where can the public
access independent third-party studies
or when can they be made available? The
city's website says the PA Department of
Envir Environmental Protection is
reviewing an air quality permit
submitted by the developer for diesel
generators and at Lancaster is
monitoring the process, but monitoring
is not the same as accountability. If
you are conducting independent reviews,
then we look forward to public access to
the findings from independent reviews.
Who from our community, not corporate
representatives, has been directly
consulted about this project and is
there record? who will be held
personally accountable if these
facilities harm residents or the
environment. If you are truly committed
to Lancaster, I would love to see you
put your commitments in writing for the
public to see. We need to reclassify
these data centers and prevent any more
from coming. The city should resend
permits immediately and restart the
zoning process with public input.
Tonight's agenda includes a motion to
amend the zoning ordinance to properly
regul regulate data centers. Let's pass
it and move swiftly. You said something
about October, but I think that's a bit
far away to be discussing this and I
think this is a more urgent issue. Um,
it's about more than permits. It's about
trust. If decisions have already been
made, share them. Share your thoughts,
your reasoning, your humanity. People
want to believe in their leaders, but
these days especially, trust is fragile
and transparency is the only way
forward. The community does not want any
more backroom discussions. Has anyone
from this council personally reached out
to the residents who spoke last time or
previous times? Responding to emails,
having real conversations, and showing
that you've done your homework would go
a long way. The public needs to see that
beyond this one meeting today. Thank you
for the information, and I would love to
see this continue. I would love to see
actual dialogue with the public ahead of
town hall style meetings and the ones
that you're referring to in October. We
are here to continue holding you
accountable and work together to push
these tech giants out. Half a million
lives in this county are at stake. We
cannot stay silent on this and we will
not. So work with us and keep working
with us. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
Mr. Harris. I believe that confirms our
list of speakers for the per first
public comment period. Is that correct?
>> I'm sorry.
>> That concludes the list of speakers.
>> Yes.
>> Thank you. I want to take a moment to
follow up and ask if Mary Jones or Kim
Keller are here. Their names were called
earlier um but they were not here when
their names were called. So if not, we
will close the first public comment uh
period. And thank you for everyone um
who commented this evening. Uh we will
continue with the rest of our agenda. I
know that some of you may be here for
just that particular portion of the
meeting. So you're welcome um to go if
you need to. You're also welcome to
stay. So thank you. Um the next item on
our agenda uh will be the capital bud
budget public hearing. Um so director
Tina Campbell will be coming forward and
um I believe counselors um earlier she
sent what she will be presenting on the
screen. Is that correct? So we'll have
it in email and on the screen.
I'll give everybody just a moment.
Good evening to both directors Campbell.
Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Harris.
>> All right. Good evening.
>> Good evening.
Um, so tonight we are holding the
capital budget hearing. This is based on
the capital improvement plan for 2026 to
2030. Um, this hearing is based on what
was presented both on June 24th and July
22nd.
Um, the plan outlines capital
improvement projects from 2026 to 2030
that are necessary for all functions of
the city. It encompasses four city
funds, the general fund, the storm water
fund, the water fund, and the sewer
fund. Um, this five-year plan includes
444 projects within these funds for a
total of approximately $300 million.
These projects consist largely of
maintenance or replacement of current
infrastructure to ensure that all
services provided by the city are
functioning as effectively as possible
for both residents and customers. And as
we've already discussed in uh in June
and in uh many more details in July, the
projects range from ensuring safe
streets for pedestrians and cyclists to
replacement of a major water main
transmission pipe, which is a once once
in a generation project.
Um as part of the home rule charter, the
city administration will present a
five-year plan annually um for approval
through city council. Additionally, we
will also report to council quarterly
for updates on the plan starting in
2026.
Should a newly construction constructed
or acquired facility be completed within
the previous quarter, um the city
administration will also report on
estimated annual costs for running and
maintaining that facility as we have
those available.
And additionally throughout this
quarterly reporting process, the city
administration will provide any updates
related to annual amort amortization
costs as additional debt is incurred. Um
the plan available for review online um
it through the website and also on the
engage lancaster um site. It includes
funding for the current approved um
general from the current approved
general obligation bonds and the current
approved pen loan Penvest loan financing
um and the current debt for each fund uh
which has already been approved through
the ordinance are included in the plans
for your review as well. And within this
five-year budget, there are some
expenses that are not yet funded and may
need uh additional debt financing as we
move towards the latter years of the
plan. Um, as the amount of this funding
becomes finalized, city administration
will report on the amortization costs of
the debt in the quarterly updates to
council. And as with any plan, these
projects will continue to evolve once
they begin or as they continue. More
precise estimates and funding sources
will be included in future capital
improvement plans as we move closer to
the start date as of some of the later
projects. And we're looking forward to
providing those updates quarterly. You
can go to the next slide.
Um because we've reviewed the capital
improvement plan and budget extensively
on both June 24th and July 22nd, I'm not
going to spend very much time reviewing
this again. Um but just wanted to
provide a highle summary again. So these
slides um there's just a few of them. Um
they are they are also available in the
documents that have been available
online for review. Um and then in
addition to uh the full list of projects
and all the details that go with each
project um including both the um
expenses by year and the funding
sources.
So there are 144 projects total as I
have mentioned and you can see here the
breakdown by general fund and the
enterprise funds. Next slide please.
Um the uh 144 capital projects include
um included on the plan total
approximately $31.4
million.
Um we have divi we have the projects
divided into six sections on this chart
but three of the sections um the parks
PW or public works admin um and streets
are all part of the general fund and
then the other three sections are
labeled based on the enterprise fund
that they're associated with. And as
we've discussed previously you can see
that the water and sewer funds have the
biggest needs that makes up
approximately twothirds of the costs.
This is not unusual for water and sewer
facilities since these utilities rely so
heavily on major infrastructure um to
function properly. Um however, this does
create some challenges of containing
debt, payment costs, and keeping fees
reasonable as we try to ensure that the
systems work well. Next slide, please.
So, here's a quick breakdown of each of
the funds. Um the general fund and the
three enterprise funds. And I'll just um
say as a reminder, the city does run a
fourth enterprise fund, the solid waste
and recycling fund. Um but most of those
services are are contracted out. So
capital costs and projects are not
included in the capital improvement plan
for that fund.
Next slide, please.
Um and also as I mentioned previously
each project must identify a funding
source or in many cases um for the
projects its funding sources um that can
be used to ensure that the project is
completed. So we've included 11 funding
sources in our capital improvement plan
though some of these are groupings
rather than specific sources. Um the
committed grant sources as an example
are are all grant funding that has been
awarded. Um but it's made up of many
individual grants. And additionally we
have an unfunded funding source that
shows a need for funding either grant or
debt funding but that source has not yet
been identified. This unfunded source is
used in the projects that are further
out in the five-year plan. So three,
four, or five years out. And each year
that we come with a new capital
improvement plan uh to approve, you'll
see that start to move to a known
funding source as those projects get
closer to its start. Um
and each of the funding sources that
we've intended to use are listed per
project in the plan that's online um and
that you've received as well.
And then next slide. And finally here
just to review a grouping of the funds.
Um this is the funding sources. Um, so
the first three categories are what we
consider committed funding. Um, so it
does not require further debt. Um, we're
currently at about 50.6 million or 51.7
million. Sorry, I had my note wrong. Um,
in bond funding. Um, that's that's
already confirmed. Um you can see there
the grant funding that we have committed
as well as uh funding from our sewer
partners which are those first three and
the remaining percent uh the remaining
amounts which is about 53% um would need
to be funded u mainly by future debt
either through penvest or bond
financing. Some of what we've identified
as unfunded um could also be eligible
for grant funding. So, we'll continue to
pursue the grant funding for projects
that are eligible um to try to keep that
future debt as low as possible.
Um and then just as a reminder, uh we
will present an ordinance for first
reading for the capital budget at the
September 9th regular meeting of council
and it'll go through the regular
ordinance ordinance process from there.
Um, finally tonight we did have one
comment on the plan that was included on
the Engage Lancaster uh website. We've
not received other comments or questions
um beyond that. So I've asked Director
Steve Campbell to review that comment
and respond this evening.
>> Thank you very very much.
The comment was related to the water
street infrastructure project which is a
combined project of water, public right
of way, transportation, storm water and
active transportation network. The
question was whether the arts component
was funded in the in the request. So the
the project itself is a multiple is a
multiple faceted project where
approximately 3.6 6 million of that
project is storm water related and
nearly 11 million of it is related to
water and sewer infrastructure as well
as public right ofway infrastructure and
the project will take place over the
course of a sixy year period or more.
The the amount of of work that we're
anticipating for the for the art element
is very very minor. We're looking at uh
at sculptural elements for the green
infrastructure, the the four bays and
the and the the rain gardens areas uh
which would would not exceed about
anywhere would be in a range from
anywhere from 12 to $40,000 all told for
the artwork. the the the person who had
made the request referenced a project
that was in Pittsburgh by a uh an artist
uh for uh for the for PennDOT that was
extraordinarily much larger than the pro
than the art investment that we're
looking at here. Um it was for a very
magnificent looking frankly um uh sound
attenuation wall that was almost a half
a mile long. uh on Route 28 outside of
Pittsburgh and it was trying to be
evocative of water and sound and a
variety of other things. It was very
very magnificent and etc. We're not
looking to do anything like that. We're
hoping that the work that we can do for
arts may actually be tied to the schools
with a STEM program might be performed
by some of the some local uh with
funding from so some local um uh sub u
funders local funders as well as s
searching continuing to search for
grants. When we had initially initi
thought about this project, we were
looking at grants that were at the time
available at the federal level, but
those grants are no longer available.
But the intention for it to be
beautified, similar to what we've done
with the storm water, storm grates,
paintings, or uh any kinds of elements
that make the way that water passes
through the the variety of
infrastructures of the city of Lancaster
accessible visually and in knowledge to
the public, whether youth or residents,
etc., is still very much important to
us. But we want to do it and need to do
it at a much more modest level. So the
simple answer is that for the budgeting
for the funds that have been requested,
it does not include the u the the arts
the arts component.
>> Thank you very much both of you um for
all of the work leading up to this
moment and the work that will be lie
ahead as we um in future meetings
introduce an ordinance to adopt the
capital budget. Uh council uh members of
council any comments on the budget
hearing this evening?
>> If I may, President Council Diaz,
>> Miss Campbell, you had mentioned um
previously when we were going over it um
the budget, you had mentioned in regards
to how much we invest in our technology
in
in city hall. Do you recall that?
>> I I believe that was in the operating
budget. Is that
>> Yes. Um my question I'm going to
diverted to this particularly if we
invest
a lot in our community tax money for our
city to run our technology.
Why is it that the AV is not working
correctly? And why would someone
scheduled a meeting and of course I was
to be present but unfortunately I was
ill and I said well since I was able to
use it through our teams that I would be
able to um attend the meeting which
obviously the response was that it's not
working correctly. So my concern is how
much do we invest in our IT and when is
it going to be fixed because it's been a
pretty long time.
>> Yeah, I I can speak to um
do you want me to speak a little bit to
the AV equipment or
>> Well, I can share what I know
specifically related to the AV equipment
and maybe just the techn technological
expenses overall. um you can address but
um yes so there there has been money
allocated for the AV equipment um for
this year uh there's a company that
we've engaged to make long needed
upgrades uh to the equipment which was I
believe secondhand when when we got it
um they are working the the timeline is
to begin next week on the project the
reason why it waited was because they
work with schools uh who took priority
uh fortunately to get their AV up and
running before the beginning of the
school year is my understanding. Um so
that project will begin next week.
Unsure exactly when it will finish. My
hope is by our September 9th meeting,
but it it's it hard to say. Um as
someone in operations, I know that
things come up and things change. Um,
and in terms of how long it's been down,
um, when you're talking about spending,
you know, 50,000 plus on an AV system,
in my opinion, uh, you want to make sure
you're buying the right one, getting the
right people to install it, and making
sure you have all the features you need.
So, a few months with some mics that
aren't ideal isn't ideal, but it is
right when you want to take the time.
So, that's my opinion, and Tina, if you
have any or director Campbell, if you
have anything additional to add.
>> Yeah. Um, yeah, thanks. I will just say
too that this is we're actually
purchasing the equipment with the grant
that we received. So, it's not coming
out of the general operating fund um
budget. Thank you so much.
Additional comments from council on the
budget hearing
and we will close the budget hearing for
this evening. Uh we look forward to
having you bringing forward the official
ordinance next month. Thank you.
We will now move into our legislative
agenda. Uh we begin with the legislative
budget transfers. I believe that's going
to come from councelor Royo.
>> Thank you. Excuse me.
Thank you, council president.
Pull up my notes here.
Thank you, council president. Um, as
you're aware, the city is self-insured
for workers compensation costs and every
year funds to pay workers compensation
claims are included in the individual
department budgets. Uh, but those claims
are paid from the administrative
services budget. So each quarter, we
shift money from the departments where
those injured workers have made claims
to the administrative services budget to
cover the costs. For the second quarter
of the year, workers comp claims were
made by the city police officers and
public works employees. A total of
$37,656.78
is being moved from moved from those
department budgets to administrative
services. Because this money is being
moved between departments, this requires
city council approval. So I make the
motion to approve the second quarter
workers compensation transfers totaling
$37,656.78
as proposed.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second.
Councilors, any additional comments on
the legislative transfers, budget
transfers,
comments from the public
hearing. None. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. Royo,
>> I.
>> Mr. Gleas,
>> Miss Diaz,
>> I.
>> Mr. Hersh,
>> I present
>> I.
Next item on the agenda is items from
the historic conservation district. Um,
generally these uh these come through
the community planning uh committee and
that would be Council Craig, Council
Royo in her place. If you would uh take
this item.
>> Thank you, Council President.
>> Oh, I'm so sorry. Well, that goes to Mr.
Harris. If you would read those for me.
>> Yes, Madam President.
>> Thank you.
>> Considering the following applications
and recommendations from the Historical
Commission for improvements to uh
properties within the Heritage
Conservation District. First is Kiana
Castro, owner of 550
proposes construction of an uncovered
stoop on the facade of a two-story brick
rowhouse. And the second is John E.
Smucker III, owner of 39 North Plum
Street, proposes construction of a
one-story frame leg room addition to the
rear of a Horner rowhouse. And both of
those applications were recommended for
approval by the historical commission.
>> I'd like to make a motion to approve
both items A and B uh for approval.
>> Second. Thank you. We have a motion and
a second. Councelor Royal.
>> Thank you, Council President. Uh nothing
much to add. Both of these items were
recommended for approval by the historic
commission and our very uh minor um uh
changes. So, nothing to add.
>> Thank you very much. Any additional
council comments on the approvals
>> from the public?
>> Hearing none. Mr. Harris,
>> Mr. Roya.
>> I,
>> Mr. Cle.
>> Miss Diaz.
>> I,
>> Mr. Hirs.
>> President Baker.
>> I,
>> that concludes our legislative agenda
this evening. The next item on our
agenda is our second public comment
period. That's open for issues that were
not previously addressed on the agenda.
Duration of comments is limited to three
minutes per speaker. Please begin with
your name and your block of residents.
If there's anyone who wishes to make
comment in this period, please proceed
to the microphone at this time.
hearing none. Well, are you making
public comment? Okay. Um, if you would
please just turn the microphone back on
and you may adjust that to wherever you
need that to go. Please begin with your
name and block of residence. Good
evening.
>> Good evening. Uh, Oakley, Buscino,
Lafayette Street. So, right, I'm gonna I
wasn't a registered speaker at the
beginning, but I'd like to make some
comments about something I discussed
earlier, which was the AI data center.
Uh I stood at this podium in March uh of
this year discussing how AI is impacting
our environment, encouraging small
businesses to turn to PCAD, which is
right next door for humanmade creative
assets. Now a $6 billion AI facility is
threatening our community with its
presence. And I find myself back here
talking about the same thing. Lancaster
is an emporium of small shops and cell
phone businesses. Its culture
constructed off of individual creations
by unique creatives. And outside of the
city, you have acres upon acres of
beautiful land and tasteful a
agriculture defining traditional
Pennsylvania. I'd like to acknowledge
the comments earlier about environmental
preservation and limited use of water,
but I'm not reassured as a resident,
especially from the lack of
transparency, that this center won't use
a major amount of water and electricity.
I previously gone over how AI has
impacted the job industry. 3,900 workers
replaced by AI, according to the
National University in March.
Entrepreneurs around the world have
faced job loss, decreases in salary, and
lack of opportunities in the market. As
you heard tonight, the construction of
the center alone will concern workers.
Imagine the detrimental effect it'll
have on future jobs in Lancaster. Let me
remind you now of the consequences this
data center will have on people who live
here. To start, these data centers will
use some sort of water for cooling, even
if it's a limited amount. And while
there are efforts to limit such, you are
still using sign significant amount of
water in a facility that's costing $6
billion to construct. Each text prompt
consuming consumes an ad fridge water
bottle. Globally, AI related
infrastructure may soon consume six
times more than water than Denmark, a
country of 6 million people, according
to a study from the University of
California. This becomes an issue when a
quarter of humanity already lacks access
to clean water and sanitation. Lancaster
res residents uh already struggle with
increasing water bills. Are you okay
with risking the lives of thousands of
Lancaster residents just to give more
money to big corporations instead of the
people? Lastly, these data centers will
emit waste such as CO2, lead, and
mercury into our environment, quickening
the effects of global warming. Whether
you like it or not, it will suck up
energy and water from Lancaster
residents, leaving citizens to live with
the consequences consequences of your
decisions. The power plant and backup
generators needed to keep data centers
working generate harmful air pollutants
such as fine particle matters of
nitrogen oxides. These pollutants take
an immediate toll on human health,
triggering asthma symptoms, heart
attacks, and even cognitive decline.
According to the E spectrum, despite
efforts a center at this scale cannot
avoid causing environmental harm, and
with lack of transparency until now, I
have little faith that it'll cause
little damage as you say it does. Please
continue to reassure the public with
accessible information on these matters.
But I'd like to thank you again for the
comments earlier. Remember, at some
point us taxpayers will have to keep
paying for the environment killing data
center. And please nobody wants to do
that. As you continue to fund this data
center,
>> I appreciate your comments. We've got
we've gone past three minutes.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> Are there any additional speakers for
the second public comment period?
Good evening.
>> Good evening.
>> Adjust that as needed. There you go.
>> Uh Brett Stanley. I live in Knville, but
I work in Lancaster.
Um I spoke last uh last meeting. I've
been here for all of them. Um I spoke on
job creation and lack thereof possibly
with uh the work in creating you know
catalysts for the data centers. SW at my
employer in Writesville, my old employer
in Writesville, um
had a hand in building a lot of uh
things for data centers whether they be
catalysts like STRs, they're selective
like SR
basically uh as one of the comments that
he had made about the um
uh the the interruption of data center
like output. Um, one of the things that
they also were making were these uh like
rolling generators or rolling data
centers to support these things.
Basically, I'm just coming here to say
more information of this seems like it's
destined to happen and basically none of
you had any say in it and doesn't seem
like we will have any say in it
retroactively
addressing the concerns. not you guys
but the
whole process in it of itself like
waiting till October um etc. But uh yeah
I
I would certainly like to stay on top of
uh where this work is coming from where
it's going and yeah I I'm just really
disheartened that it seems like the work
is already done and it's just being
upon our community.
I hope that you all can have some
influence on that. Uh I didn't really
have a choice in like what I make. It's
just custom fabrication. So you get a
new job almost every day, new parts. But
anyway, wasting a little bit of time.
Thanks. That's all I had.
>> Thank you.
>> Any additional comments for this period?
Good evening.
>> Good evening. Hi, Jeannie Showers from
Mountainville. Uh, first I want to thank
the council for addressing uh, you know,
some of the questions that the public
had had in previous meetings and so
forth. I definitely think that it has
assuaged some of our worries and
concerns, especially with regards to the
environmental impacts, uh, specifically
with water. Um however moving forward I
do want to at least you know urge the
council to be mindful of the
enforcability of the proposed
regulations with um you know even though
uh there will be an agreement a legally
binding agreement with water consumption
we want the public we want to make sure
that that is being maintained um as
objectively as possible. possible.
Additionally, we want to ensure that
moving forward uh the environmental
agencies that have been hired to conduct
um you know the noise
um studies and so forth are
uh you know unaffiliated with these data
centers and with um you know corporate
backing behind it. Uh we also want to
ensure that moving forward in the future
uh we want to ensure that when these
data centers do potentially expand that
they um remain within the footprint of
the existing uh structure as it is
stated in the FQA online
and uh
if they do expand beyond that if the
current or proposed zoning ordinances
that are likely to be changed that the
expansion is in is in accordance with
those newer zoning ordinances.
Um and lastly, just wanting to urge the
council to be mindful of the strain on
the energy grid. Um I like I like you
had mentioned previously even though you
do not have control over um the energy
within Lancaster. Um
I am curious as a resident what will be
done with the grid in order to bolster
it so that it can um
support not only the data center but the
residents as well which will have you
know the largest impact um from these
data centers. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Are there any other commenters for this
period?
Good evening.
>> Good evening. Uh my name is Mick Whid. I
live just outside the city on Columbia
A. Um I just wanted to request the
council's help in pressuring the zoning
officer and the mayor in showing up to
any of the hearing uh hearings that are
being proposed. Um, as I've heard from
other sources, the zoning officer has no
interest in showing up to those and
answering questions, which feels shady,
and I don't like that. And I'm sure we
would all love some answers from the
actual people involved in making these
decisions that we know you guys weren't
allowed to be involved in. That's all.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Any additional commenters for this
period?
I would encourage anyone else who wishes
to just line up just so we can save a
couple of minutes if possible, but
>> that's your prerogative.
>> Good evening.
>> I don't know number 67 South Franks
Franklin. Anyways,
>> and your name? Sorry,
>> Ro Potter.
>> Thank you. Um, I don't plan on pulling
any punches with this one, so I'm going
to try and be quick. But artificial
intelligence is the tool of fascism.
Everything ranging from AI images to
generative texts to Palunteer all plays
into their they being fascists
authoritarian agenda. despite water
cooling and emissions being supposedly
regulated, which isn't enough to comfort
me or really anyone in here who's been
paying attention to anything going on
with XAI uh down in Memphis, Tennessee.
Uh yeah, just it's just not convincing
enough. And uh stuff like this, like
like I said about Memphis, Tennessee
with XAI, stuff like this
disproportionately affects black and
brown communities, which we have a
majority of in Lancaster. And day in and
day out, we are not only pushed and
edged further out by gentrification. And
you know, the way we treat homelessness
is absolutely terrible. In the 25 years
I've been here, I just think that
something like this has no belonging in
Langster County at all. It doesn't
benefit the people that live here. Our
water is already questionable. Our
energy is already questionable. My Who
else's rent is going up, right? My
rent's up. My water is the same. It
tastes the same. But stuff like this
really no place in Lancaster County at
all. I don't see how we can take time to
put a supposed warehouse of
supercomputers when we stop potholes
right next door to it. It doesn't make
any sense. If we want to improve what's
going on in the city and you know energy
related things, I don't think putting a
giant succubus in the middle of it is
going to help anything. Um,
yeah. I just really want to stand on the
fact that artificial intelligence is the
tool of fascism.
If you want proof of that, look at the
White House's Twitter posts. There
there's not an artist you could hire out
here in the world that would do art of
alligator Alcatraz. You know,
historically when black and brown
communities have been disproportionately
affected by stuff like that.
Uh yeah, just really disgusted that this
is coming to our community in a place
where we value not only what we create
with our hands, but who we give it to.
And AI doesn't do any of that. It takes
away who's making it and don't give a
who's going to. So if you care
about living here, which I'm pretty sure
you do,
this ain't going to happen. But again,
like someone else said here, it don't
seem like we got much of an opinion or
decision. So kind of authoritarian and
oppressive.
>> Thank you.
Any additional comments for this period?
>> Hearing none, I'll close the second
public comment period and thank everyone
for participating this evening. Uh we do
have a few more items on the agenda um
just as a response to some of the latest
comments. I also was thinking um about
some shared concerns uh that I believe
we all have and uh just a thought that I
would leave everyone that we should also
be very concerned about our burough
councils and township boards of
supervisors in the rest of Lancaster
County uh in places that have vast
amounts of open space. Um I I'm not
saying this from a place that I know of
anything. I'm just saying that if that
is a concern that we all have about our
shared community, um our resources and
the air we breathe and the water we
drink and our power grid, uh then we
also should be turning to our attention
to those legislative bodies out in the
county and beyond. So, thank you. Um the
next item on our agenda is the report of
the mayor. Um she could not be here this
evening and I did deliver some comments
that she shared with me earlier. Next
item was a report of president of
council which we moved to the beginning
of the meeting. U so the next item is
comments from council. Any council
comments this evening?
>> Council President, if I may.
>> Councelor Royo.
>> Uh just very briefly, uh wanted to thank
uh our folks for coming out tonight to
continue to advocate for how we want our
community to be built in the future and
uh sharing information. Also love the
graphics that were also brought up here
earlier. So, thank you for all your hard
work on that. Um, one thing I do want to
um, express is uh, one of my biggest
frustrations since serving on council is
the realization that uh, many things
that affect directly affect the quality
of life of our residents sometimes
doesn't fall within control of council.
Um, one of the things that has come up
in uh the last couple of months is the
Pennsylvania rateayer protection act uh
which I believe has been floating around
in the state senate uh which would um
hold data centers specifically
responsible for the energy consumption
that they consume and not pass along the
burden to uh residential rateayers. Um
that is something that uh as I know
council here is advocating individually
uh to our state representatives and
state senators. Um I would implore that
all of you also do the same. They are
listening to you and a lot of the
regulations that come with data centers
will have to come from the state level.
Uh municipalities won't be able to do
this on their own. So as mentioned while
the city of Lancaster is currently deal
dealing with us other municipalities
have also been proposed with data
centers and if it just falls right
outside the boundary of Lancaster city
it is it continues to be outside of our
control but would still affect all of
you. So, um, highly highly encourage you
all to continue to, um, to advocate not
just only to us and hold us accountable,
but make sure you're also doing it on
the state level because that's really
where we're going to be able to, um,
have some influence on on data centers
and how they affect our communities u
from now into the future. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Councelor Royo.
Uh, we have now reached the conclusion
of our agenda. I will hear a motion to
adjurnn.
>> Motion to adjurnn. Second.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second.
All in favor?
>> I I We're adjourned. Thank you.